You know what? Like maybe this
ultimately is my final level.
>> This is Philip Sue. He grew quickly to a
distinguished [music] engineer or IC9 at
Facebook and then OpenAI. And I
interviewed him about the psychology of
peing in your career. When I got to
seven, you know, I felt like, hm, this
is pretty much nearing the boundary of
my capability. It's like when Beaolf at
age 70 is asked to like slay the dragon
one last time. Part of me wishes that I
had that in me. Do you think that you'd
be happier if you got promoted slower? I
feel like titrating it out would have
been better for me. Here's the full
episode.
Last time we talked, I focused almost
entirely on you got to distinguish
engineering level. You grew very
quickly. How'd you do it? And this time
I wanted to focus more on what happens
when you hit your terminal level or what
I mean is there's this idea of a career
asmtote which is no no one can grow
forever and at some point you're going
to get to a level where you can't go any
further and you may have 20 30 years
left in the career. So what I wanted to
ask you is, you know, when you got
promoted to IC9 or distinguished
engineer, which is crazy high, that's
like four levels higher than a senior
engineer.
What was your immediate thought? Were
you thinking, I want to go to ICT10?
Does that exist? Or were you thinking
something entirely different?
>> Yeah, I think when I started, I honestly
didn't think about it. When I was
earlier in career, I really just assumed
that oh yeah, you go for a promotion and
once every few years you get promoted
and I never once thought there's got to
be an end to this, right? [laughter]
Like everybody there's got to be an end,
right? And I think many people might not
think that through, right? And so for me
it took many years before I figured out,
you know, even at seven, for instance, I
felt like, oh, hey, things have got to
slow down because, you know, it it gets
harder and harder. the amount of scope
that you need um becomes tougher. The
number of roles that offer the
opportunity actually gets smaller
because the organization needs to also
need that scope of work, right? So for
instance at Microsoft oftentimes when
they reorganize, they figured out, hey,
your organization should at most have
four partners and that's just a
budgetary sort of thing. That's a
business opportunity thing. So you need
the opportunity as well. And so when I
was growing to nine, I think I just
didn't think of going any further as
realistic. I was at Facebook when they
first created level 9, right? Um, and I
remember that three level eights were
promoted into nine. And at that point,
those three level eights were all
universally loved and known throughout
the company as obviously super senior
technical people. And to me, [snorts]
that felt unreachable if I'm honest.
when I think about those folks and the
type of work they were doing that really
felt out of reach for me. So I think
definitely by the time I got to eight or
nine it really felt like you know the
end is near. Well a lot of people might
feel that sooner in their career too.
What kept you pushing past the staff
level or the senior staff level, you
know, six, seven, eight, nine?
>> When I got all the way through to seven,
I think, which was at my 12 years at
Microsoft, right? I was really
personally ambitious for level growth.
And I think the reason was in schools, I
love tests. I love grades because I was
good at grades and tests. When I started
professional work, there was nothing
quantifiable. like it wasn't like once
every two months you got a test that
told you you you were doing well. So for
me, promotions became one of the very
few quantifiable things, right? It's
sort of like, well, how much money do I
make? And like there are so few things
that are actually numbers, right? So to
me, a level was almost like an
achievement number. And so throughout my
20s and my early 30s, I was really
ambitious to get through um all the way
to level seven. But I think starting
there, I just realized, you know, the
nature of the work changes with every
additional level that you go into. I
wasn't sure that I would like the nature
of work first of all and then the other
is I felt things slowing down rightfully
because everybody has a talent limit
right so for me as I approached that I
just began to feel like you know I was
no longer ambitious for the further
growth so I would say my growth into
eight and nine neither of those were
things that I was seeking myself I was
by that point doing the work I found
interesting and trying to do a better
job of it as opposed to I would
characterize my time, especially in my
20s, as mostly focused on how do I grow
to the next level? Tell me what I need
to do, like that sort of thing. By the
time I went from seven to eight, getting
to eight was honestly a surprise for me
at Facebook because getting to eight was
the first time I learned that there were
levels at Facebook. When I joined
Facebook, it was 500 engineers, right?
Um, everybody was focused on the work
itself and did not worry about careers
and stuff, which I think is normal for
small companies when you're on a big
mission. You're just trying to get the
mission done. So, I didn't even learn I
had a level until my boss, who was Bos,
right? Uh, said, "Hey, congratulations.
You've been promoted to level eight."
And I was like, "What? There's a level
here?" Like, that's kind of amazing.
Thank you. Right. So I think I stopped
focusing on the level itself and my
promotions became more a consequence of
the work that was being done.
>> Early in your career, it sounds like you
you were constantly maybe harping your
manager and you say, "How can I get
promoted? What's the next thing?" And
later you transitioned into
uh doing meaningful work and getting
promoted as a byproduct. What was it
that changed in your mind where you went
from that mentality to
promos don't matter anymore?
>> Yeah, I think there were two things that
come to mind. One was that the thrill of
the promotion itself was no longer the
same as when I was younger. So I think
when I was younger because I sought
after those grades, those measurable
metrics, I very much felt great every
time I got promoted. This was like
wonderful, right? I think as I got
promoted, even into level seven, I
started to honestly become a little bit
not ambivalent about it, but I guess it
wasn't all roses to me anymore, the idea
of getting promoted because I realized
that each promotion also came with much
higher expectations. Expectations that I
was no longer positive that I was going
to deliver well. You know what I mean?
When I went from a four to a five, you
know, I was confident that I could do
this work like it'll be great, right?
when I got to seven, you know, I felt
like this is pretty much nearing the
boundary of my capability and so I felt
a lot more comfortable um saying like
hey if they keep me here perpetually it
is still work I enjoy a lot. I think the
second thing that really changed for me
um is realizing also that asmmptote
right realizing that you know what like
maybe this ultimately is my final level.
Um, I was so humbled many years ago when
um, I've had this lifelong mentor
throughout much of my adult life that
was one of my best managers at
Microsoft. And I recently just in the
last few years thought, you know, there
was this one conversation where he
promoted me into level seven. And I said
to him, that's great. Thank you. Let's
talk about how to get to eight, right?
And his first response to me was like,
"Phil, can we just take at least one
one-on-one to celebrate the fact that
you've actually reached this tremendous
level at Microsoft?" And I honestly felt
like, "No, like we can't like I've got
to keep going." But years later, I
realized, you know, he himself was
probably 15 years more in industry than
I was at the time. And he himself, in
hindsight, had to be a level seven. He
was not a partner at Microsoft. And so
for me to come across sort of so naively
like without considering for instance
his feelings or considering just
realistically this is a guy I look up to
a lot and he's giving me mentoring
advice all the time and he himself is
level seven and so for me to like be
pushing so hard. I think just the
humility of realizing that you know what
like people do tremendous work at those
levels and I should just appreciate that
if I can even keep up with the
expectations that's already kind of a
big accomplishment.
If I were to think from when I was you
at my youngest to the beginning of the
career, my thought would have been
keep pushing. And the thoughts that you
just said are uh they're noble, but
let's let's go to eight. Let's go. Yes,
this person's that level, but I want
more. I want more. What what calmed the
I guess the gut crazy energy of I want
more even if it's not realistic. I think
some of it might be as simple as age to
be honest. And I think society is
designed to work this way, right? Like
young people go to war, right?
Traditionally, and like there needs to
be like this ambition of like I'm going
to build great things. I'm going to do
great things. I think that energy from
the young is super powerful. And I
definitely don't want to sit here and
say let's quell all of that. Like let's
make sure when a person is 23 and they
start work they're like you know like E3
is fine right? So I definitely want
people to have that ambition. I think
maybe some of it is the natural aging
process but I think do think at least
for myself a lot of it was the shifting
nature of the job itself. I would say
for me up until let's say an IC6 level
of work it just felt like doing the same
stuff but grander if that makes sense
like you're still coding all day you're
like meeting with engineers primarily
and product managers sometimes designers
but it's just about doing like at a much
higher amplitude you know I'm now going
to like do much bigger refactors I'm
going to like participate in longer
range projects like oh we should like do
this new service that does X but I think
beyond that the nature really changes to
where like just doing more better is
typically not how people get there. You
will have find very rare cases for
instance where people can do more better
but they are like prednaturally like
gifted for you know super fast coding or
whatever. I was definitely not that
person because I was much more a
generalist and so for a generalist going
beyond six I think it does change the
nature of the work such that you're
doing maybe less direct coding for
instance maybe even less direct
architecture stuff but much more things
like team direction you know is this
even the right product to be building
right now given where the industry is
moving maybe trying to influence even
another organization that's on a
collision path right like maybe trying
to find a mutually you know useful way
to land both sides So I think that also
you know take pragmatically as you go up
higher in levels it's almost definitely
true that you will have more meetings
just period [laughter] whether you're an
IC whether you're a manager that's just
what it is and you know plenty of people
for whom like directors as an example
every single hour is meetings and half
of the hours are double booked and so
they're just choosing which one to go to
like for that right that's typically how
like one small example of how the nature
of the work changes and so for me as the
nature of work changes
you know, I was less enthused about um
you know, how it might continue to
change if I continued getting higher
level.
>> You mentioned that you sought out a
demotion from IC9 to IC7 or
distinguished to senior staff. Did you
ever consider saying to your manager, I
don't want to get promoted past IC7?
>> From going to 7 to 8, not really because
I didn't know levels had existed at that
point. So like that promotion was sort
of like surprise, right? Um, but I think
if I'm honest, Facebook was also so
small even back then I was promoted into
eight maybe one year at Facebook. I was
a seven at Microsoft for probably three
years. So you figure like let's say four
years, right? One year into Facebook I
get promoted to eight. Facebook was
still I want to say back then 800
engineers globally. So so the company
was much smaller. And I think when a
company is that size I think the work
doesn't include as much meta work. You
know what I mean? like the work is
mostly the work so you're like doing the
code you're doing the actual right
whereas I would say my experience even
of Facebook many years later you know
when I came back to Facebook Seattle you
know um when I joined I was the second
person who joined right so the office
was four desks when I went to London for
5 years and I came back the office was
more than 2,000 people and so just like
that mind-blowing size means that the
typical senior job when an organization
is tens of thousands of people is a lot
more people wrangling I guess and a lot
more
I don't know a lot less technical. I
think one of the struggles I've had
throughout my career is so many higher
level jobs including a solid IC6 quote
unquote just coding has to do with how
well they work with others and I in some
environments just don't work very well
with people like I in others do. I would
say objectively when I was leading the
Facebook London site, I was good at the
job. It was a very people focused job,
but it was for me the happy parts of
people like welcome to the team or like
hey we're going to like do this
collaboration with Menel Park and all
this stuff. I think there's another type
of people oriented thing that happens at
large companies which is a lot of what
people might call politics but a lot of
sort of work that has nothing to do with
the actual software deliverable but has
everything to do with the fact that when
three or more people are somewhere
there's politics right and like just
figuring out the people thing dealing
with unhappy people for instance is
something I'm very bad at um giving
people constructive feedback is
something that I am fairly really bad
at. And so more jobs at those levels
just require even an IC7 minding his own
business is probably regularly supposed
to be giving pretty helpful feedback to
other engineers. You know, they're not
their managers, but still you should be
improving those around you. And I am
much less good at that. when you sought
out the demotion from IC9 to IC7, I'm
just thinking for someone who's thinking
that the success criteria is going up in
levels, it would be very difficult to
accept going down from, you know, kind
of like undoing all that hard work,
quote unquote. What was that process
like? I think it was hard. Um I think it
was Will Smith or someone else famous
said like getting famous is amazing
being famous is a mixed bag and then
getting not famous is horrible
[laughter] right and I think that's
human nature not just about fame but
about anything right when we are growing
in anything like let's suppose you first
get into auto repair right the first big
job you do beyond an oil change feels
like success right eventually you've
like removed an engine you've like done
clutches right and at some point like my
age right now I literally just started
giving away some of my my auto repair
gear because I'm realizing you know I'm
not doing this as much like physically
I'm not as capable of doing it and that
feels a little bit sad and I think the
same thing happened to me in uh my
software career which is on the way
rising up it always felt great right
other than the rising expectations and
the worries around that but the general
thing felt like oh I'm progressing um
being at the top was a mixed bag. You
know, there were some amazing things,
there were some very hard things. And
then I think coming down, I feel like
there were a few things that were hard
about it. One was that I think I I knew
I could do more, you know, because I had
done more before, but part of it was the
feeling of being exhausted running at
that pace and always having the eye of
Sauron like roving the land looking for
people, right? And I think the higher
level you are, the more that you feel
that intensity all the time and
rightfully so, like you're getting paid
the big bucks and so it's right for a
company to say you you know constantly
question whether or not they are getting
their value out of you. So I think it's
only fair but I felt that struggle. And
I think the other thing that was hard
for me about getting demoted down to
seven was more that feeling that as I
saw other people who used to be below me
rise above me beyond that level. That
was very difficult. I don't begrudge
them their success. So I'm not at all
saying like I'd rather go out there and
make sure this person never succeeds.
What I mean is more that um I felt
wistful I guess is the right word which
is like I was not crushed that someone
else was doing better but I did feel a
little bit like I once could do that
work and part of me wonders if I could
again right it's like when Beaolf at age
70 is asked to like slay the dragon one
last time like he gets out of his his
old you know house and he's like and he
slays the dragon one last time part of
me wishes that I had that in me that
like when I'm 70 I can be called upon
one last time to do this thing Right.
And I'm able to deliver at that level,
but I know [snorts] that maybe that's
not it for me. Right.
>> You mentioned that you used to be able
to do it and then you couldn't. What
What changed that made it hard to
perform at that level?
>> I think if I were to
buck it into a few categories. One is my
environment changed. So as Facebook the
company grew, right? Um senior IC's do a
lot better I think in tiny uh in in
larger companies if they are domain
experts. So you're great at, let's say,
SQL optimization, right? And like you're
helping SQL move on to SSD and you're
moving SQL into the cloud. Um, that sort
of IC does best in a large company. In a
tiny company, a generalist does best
because like when I first started on
video calling, I also negotiated like
the contracts with Skype, with a third
party tester, like with all sorts of
things. So I'm like negotiating
contracts. I'm like doing crazy things,
but I'm also coding the thing. And then
when the press release goes out, I'm
talking to the press. So, I'm literally
meeting the press about the video
calling feature, right? That is what a
generalist excels at. And I could only
do that because Facebook was small. By
the time I came back to Facebook Seattle
and the Seattle office itself was 2,000
plus people and the company was maybe, I
don't know, 30,000 people. There's no
way you would send me out to negotiate a
contract [laughter] with like Microsoft.
That would be ridiculous, right? And so,
for me as a generalist, my environment
shifted to where specialists would
survive better. And for me as a
generalist, I was honestly just not as
useful, right? Like for one whole
six-month period, the team that I was
on, the only mission for the IC's for
that entire six months was fix the bugs
on this internal tool. So I spent six
months fixing the bugs, which I'm happy
to do, but I am not especially skilled
at that, right? And so I think one thing
was my environment changed. I think the
other thing that changed for me was I
did tire a little bit of feeling like
there was always so much pressure just
to meet expectations, if that makes
sense. Um, so up until I would say IC6,
um, I never felt the eye of Sauron. Like
I I was never at any point in my career
feeling like, oh, if I just fall a
little below right now, maybe they're
going to can me, right? Um, but I think
regularly at seven and beyond, once in a
while, I would feel like, ooh, like I
feel like my own performance this half,
I don't know, like things aren't looking
[laughter] great. You know what I mean?
And I think in a way it's like when I
was super ambitious, being like the
slowest member of a team, but catching
up and rising was exciting to me. As I
accomplished more in my career and I
felt my happy places, I no longer like
the feeling of being slowest on a team
or feeling like I was potentially going
to have a talking to at some point
because I wasn't performing on
expectations. So I think that that sort
of pressure also was something that I no
longer enjoyed. In reality that Eye of
Sauron though was um in your head rather
than reality given that you got promoted
from 7 to 8 and 8 to 9, right?
>> Yes. Maybe some of it is imposttor
syndrome but I think a lot of it is
actually just an honest look at myself
and reality. So when I was an IC4
looking to go to IC5, right? There were
plenty of IC5s where I felt like I could
totally do that work like [laughter]
like just give me two years and I'll be
just as good, right? at IC7 I could see
many IC7s where I'm like honestly if you
put me on that guy's team I could not do
that work like right like I I know I
can't right and and so I think my
realistic appraisal of my own abilities
was I think more accurate [laughter] to
to what they actually were um and also
maybe some of it you know if I riff on
your theme a little bit maybe some of it
also is that um as you get more and more
senior here. Not only are the
expectations higher, but the number of
business roles where you are the perfect
guy for the role actually is far far
less.
So when you're an IC6, almost any team
would welcome one. It's like great, like
just pick up a keyboard and like we'll
get going. But I think once you get to a
certain level, it's like, well, we need
someone who's good at like we need
someone who's good at marketing and then
this person has to also be somewhat
technical or like the shapes become very
specific, right? And I think that just
realizing that my shape wasn't right for
many, many roles also made me
realistically feel like maybe this isn't
the right long-term place for me. It
sounds like over the course of your
career, you worked an extraordinary
amount. I mean, you mentioned last time
we talked that you bring a sleeping bag
to work, [laughter]
you know, and I think early in your
career it it makes a lot of sense cuz
you were so gung-ho and you were
pursuing the promos, but then when you
were at Facebook and you weren't
pursuing the promos, you were just
getting them because you were doing
awesome work. What was your motivation
to work so so crazy hours at that time?
One of the most intense work periods of
my life was shipping the first version
of Facebook video calling. You know, um
I had worked with uh Denise, with Chago,
with maybe one or two other with VJ. Um
that first version when we went out, I
think I went about six weeks down in
Menllo Park where I literally got up out
of bed, went in straight to work and
worked all the way until I drove back to
the apartment and went to sleep. I was
eating junk food the whole day. It was
like sun chips and like whatever. But
despite that, I lost 10 pounds in those
six weeks. Oh my god. It goes to show
like how intense like brain related work
can be. But I had a no idea there were
levels. So obviously a promotion was
nowhere on my mind when I was doing this
work. But I tell you, it was one of the
most fun periods of my life because it
felt so thrilling that I was directly
impacting like real users because
Facebook was so tiny back then. Like you
could see the users having errors right
away. I was patching errors every day.
Like it felt like missional, right? It
felt like this was the first time video
calling was going to be easy for people
without installing any software. Web RTC
was relatively new back then. we still
had to get some software with the first
version out. And so I felt like the
strong sense of mission and being on a
tiny team of like three people also felt
like wow I owe it to the other folks too
who are working equally hard to like
pull forward, right? So I think that was
still in it for me but no longer based
on um promotions as a thing but more
like I believed in what I was doing and
I felt that direct um direct customer
contact with people I could actually see
getting impacted positively by the
fixes.
>> When you look back on a career of
working so many hours, would you say
that it's worth it and would you
recommend it to others? I think it's
become popular for successful people to
tell people not to push as hard and for
wealthy people to tell people to not
push us hard. And it's understandable
that people who aren't as late in their
career or aren't as wealthy would say,
"Well, it's easy for you to say that."
Like, right, because you've already
gotten the like I once had a guy say to
me like, "Well, it's easy for you to say
that because you've already been there,
done that." And I think at some level,
yes. Um, but I also think that
there is sometimes wisdom that can only
be gotten when you live a certain thing
yourself. This is why when someone tells
you u money can't buy happiness, nobody
believes it, right? Everybody thinks
they'll be the one exception. And I
think the thing is like
you you have to have lived a certain
life before to really objectively be
able to say whether it's better or not.
And I think for me um given my
personality I think the really much
higher level roles that require broad
impact and feel like a lot of pressure
for me people-wise just for my own
personality over time is not the right
thing. But I would at the same time say
well I don't want to look at gift horse
in the mouth like the freedom for me to
for instance work on my own software
right now. It only comes from having had
a career where I got paid enough that I
could save enough money that I can go
two years writing my own software,
right? Um, and I don't want to look that
in the mouth and say like, oh no, like I
totally shouldn't have done that. Like
that's not true at all. Like I think
what it is for me is um I would have
appreciated when I was younger being
more cognizant of the trade-offs that I
was making, you know, like hey, if I
like dig in really hard right now and I
really work hard, then this will buy me
the freedom when I'm 50 to work two
years on my own software. Like I wish I
knew that was the trade-off. Whereas I
think at the time I was just blindly
pushing forward of like, hey, like I'm
just ambitious. I want to do all this
stuff.
>> And in your career, in your life in
general, you must have mentored so many
people. And like you said, if you give
someone advice and then but they can't
really take it until they actually
experience it, is all advice useless
then [laughter]
like what's the point? I think there is
still a point which is there's a massive
difference between you ignoring advice
and you not knowing the advice was even
there. And I think the difference is two
things. One is when you have the advice
in the back of your head, but you're
ignoring it. When eventually some
consequence comes about, it actually
will reinforce for you why the advice
was given and you're much more likely to
take more immediate action because it
rings true, right? And so when someone
tells you money won't buy happiness and
let's say a brick of $2 million falls on
your forehead, right? Um um and then you
go out and you buy something and you
realize it's not a happy thing. Like one
of the things that I splurged on for
myself when I felt like I have financial
security is I bought a $50 pen, okay?
Because the New York magazine said this
is the best pen out of the 100 they
reviewed. And it was this Baron Fig pen
out [clears throat] of machined aluminum
or something. And I bought that pen and
after using it a while I realized this
is not my favorite pen. Like there's a
G2 Pilot or whatever that's like much
better than this and it's like a buck
50, right? Um it took me buying that
aluminum mil pen before I'm like
actually if you mill a pen exactly
round, no matter what surface you put it
on, it's about to roll off, right?
[laughter] And like it's like hard to
grip onto because it's slippery. Um it
it takes getting there. So I I think
part of the advice is when you finally
do like buy that pen and you're
disappointed by it, you realize, hey,
people used to tell me that this thing
might happen, right? So I I think that
recognition is helpful. I think the
other thing, however, is even if you
don't take someone's advice right away,
I do think at least for me, when I next
face a decision where that advice might
apply, it makes me think a little more
hard about it. You know, like I may not
take the advice, but I'll at least
think, you know, several very smart
people have told me, you know, this
thing. Maybe there's a reason that they
say that. Open AAI, Enthropic, Cursor,
and Versel all use this product to make
their lives better. And the problem it
solves is when you're building SAS or an
AI product and you want to sell to other
companies, there's all these
requirements you need to meet. There's
SSO, there's skim, there's arbback,
there's audit logs. These are all things
that take time to integrate but aren't
the main focus of your app. Work OS is
an API layer that lets you meet all of
these requirements in just a few lines
of code. So let's say you have a new SAS
product and you want to sell to other
companies. Work OS will solve all of
these critical feature gaps for you. You
can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started. And I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast. Jira by
Atlassian isn't just for tracking work
anymore. Now you can pick your favorite
AI agent to assign tasks to and they'll
get access to the rich context that's
already in Jira. When the agent is done,
it surfaces poll request. That way you
can get more done with your favorite
agents all in one place. Learn more at
jira.dev. That's jir.dev.
Appreciate them for sponsoring the
podcast. And back to the show. Obviously
[snorts] part of career and like what
motivates people at some point is the
financial earnings and um uh I'm curious
to explore the topic of the motivation
after those more objective things
because for instance there's this this
subreddit and this movement on you know
financial independence and all of that
and I remember when I used to look at
that subreddit um there would be a
recurring post of someone saying hey I
finally did it I finally hit my
retirement number and I'm depressed or I
don't I don't know what to do because
they've been on this uh money-making
hamster wheel for such a long time that
their happiness was kind of tied to
that. And so at some point in your
career, you you broke out of that
needing to be on that that wheel. What
did you look to that gave you meaning
and fulfillment in your day-to-day
outside of needing to be in this
capitalist machine?
I feel like to your point about the fire
movement, I think there are two types of
personalities. There's one type which
when retired will be happy and they will
be happy for years. You know this is the
type of person that is happy to sit on a
beach, read a book and if they are doing
that two months from now they are still
happy. It's like oh this is the best
right? There's another type of
personality which is mine which is the
first week on the beach is amazing and
then once I'm there for two weeks I'm
like what what's going on? like what am
I doing here? For me, 4 months on a
beach feels like quote unquote a waste.
And I know that that offends many
people. Like for the type of personality
for whom lifelong beach them is amazing,
they will feel like what I'm saying is
nonsensical. But I think there's a type
of personality that ex that understands
exactly what I'm saying, which is like
that sort of person feels like, you
know, the rat in the cage that pushes
the dopamine button and then like dies
pushing it because it can't even bother
to eat because it feels the pleasure is
so great that it can't eat. When I see
that, I feel like that's sad. Like that
to me is sad. That is not dying in
bliss. Like there's a type of
personality that says, "What more could
you want?" Like if you could feel a
sensation that is more desirable than
even food when you're starving. Like
wouldn't that be the epitome of
happiness? And in my mind, that is just
travesty. Like like to me, it feels like
this rat could have been so much more.
Right? So that's how I feel about
myself. So I would say of the fire
movement for someone like me the best
parts of the fire movement for if I were
to embrace it myself which I never did
but if I were to embrace it the best
part would have been before I retired
because it gave me such a strong sense
of purpose I am going to save up until I
have $1.5 million that's the goal and
like every two months I can like
reme-measure how the investments are
doing right that is the excitement like
the moment I reach the R in fire
>> [laughter]
>> And that's actually probably the
dangerous spot for me. So I think in my
particular case for my personality
always having that sense of a goal is
good. And that is what I've struggled
with when I have been in periods of
unemployment. I've really struggled with
like what what quote unquote should I be
doing. So then I guess question is so
you you can think of getting promoted
and all all this stuff in engineering as
this this game that you're playing and
you got a goal and you're kind of going
up and you're excited. Oh, I want to go
to that next one. Oh, I want to go to
the next one. I'm going to grow the
skills. Do you think that you'd be
happier if you got promoted slower and
the game lasted your whole career? So
let's say whenever it is you actually
want to retire say I don't know 65 or
whatever the age is and we could we
could set up that game so that you are
constantly searching for that next goal
and you get IC9 at 65 and you get you
know a nice little hit of dopamine all
along the way and you're constantly
growing you know do you think you'd be
happier in that case versus you speedrun
everything and you get to IC9 9 in the
first, you know, third of the game.
>> I feel like titrating it out would have
been better for me. Maybe not all the
way till 65, let's say, right? But like
take from E3 to E9 is about six levels,
right? If you work about 42 years in
your career, that's one level promo
every seven years. When I imagine myself
taking seven years to go from three to
four, I'd feel like, oh man, I'd feel
like I was so like um behind in the
sense that it's not a competition, but I
would feel like, you know, am I really
progressing? Because seven years you
could get a PhD at Stanford, right, in
[laughter] in seven years. So I'm like,
dude, what like what's what's going on,
right? But the lema or the correlary of
what I'm saying then is let's suppose
you get from three to five or six within
let's say seven years which is like a
leisurely not superstar pace but not
like terrible pace like you go from E3
to six in let's say seven or eight years
right the remaining three levels let's
say you would need about 12 years
between each of them for the math to
work and when I think about 12 years I
also feel like oh that feels so long
like I worked at Microsoft 12 years and
that was on six different teams, right?
So, on one hand, I feel like it would be
better if it came sooner, you know, but
on the other hand, I do feel like you'd
have to recognize if it came sooner that
you might be 25 years uh in your career
without a promotion. And for me, I think
I would have to, if I were in my 20s and
you told me that, I would have to have
shifted my intrinsic motivation to
something beyond career levels. And in
my 20s, I didn't have other intrinsic
motivations. Like, so that would have
been disappointing for me. I'll throw in
one last thought, though. The median age
of a Corvette owner in America is 64.
And so, and and that's a medium, meaning
half the people are are are above that,
right? Um, I personally imagine by the
time I'm 64, owning a Corvette would be
not half as interesting as when I was
38. You know what I mean? And so in a
sense, I mean, is reaching E9 at 62 like
like as good? Is that like getting a
Corvette at 64? I don't know. Like I
feel like in a way maybe that progress
is wasted on someone that that's that's
that late in career. So I'm torn about
it. You mentioned in between jobs or
when you were um Yeah, when you're in
between jobs, the motivation or the
goals were harder. Did you ever discover
meaning or fulfillment outside of an
immediate I guess goal or you know do
you have any advice on finding meaning
in your work?
>> Yeah, very personality dependent but for
me the thing I learned about myself is
that I need to do more stuff with
people. You know what I got out of work
a big part of it was the socialization
like you show up you know it's like they
mandatorily have to show up whereas when
I throw a party nobody mandatorily has
to show up. So work is like mandatory
socialization. But when I first quit um
Facebook and I took six months off, I
thought this would be amazing. I'm going
to reach out to all sorts of longlost
former co-worker friends for coffee and
whatnot. But the problem is everybody
else was busy working. So when I wrote
them like, "Hey, can you grab a coffee?"
Whatever. It's like, "Well, I can't like
maybe next week." Right? And so what I
figured out there was that wow, like I
thought I would have all this
socialization, but I didn't. The best
time being without work was I had about
a six or a ninemonth period where two
other former co-workers of mine also
were between jobs and that was amazing.
Like we went skiing three times a week
on weekdays, right? Like we did all
sorts of stuff together. We ate dinner
out. And I imagine that's what I would
like to think British aristocrats in the
1800s like the same men that dug up like
the bones from the Jurassic region and
that's why it's called the Jurassic era,
right? Like those people, right? um the
gentleman scientists, right? I would
like to think that part of the secret to
the happiness of the aristocracy is
actually that there were other
aristocrats also looking to do something
together, you know, like it was fun
because like you you know Mr. Darcy had
no job but you have no job either. So
you and Mr. Darcy get together three
times a week to you know whatever play
botchi ball. So, I feel like that is the
secret for me. And realizing that has
made me feel like whether I'm working or
not working, being in a situation where
I can find regular socialization is
probably key to me being happier.
Do you have any book recommendation?
Something that you've read that gave you
perspective on life that you recommend
to someone who maybe earlier in their
career are still figuring out how they
want to plan things out.
>> Yes, I love the book 4,000 Weeks. I'm
not sure if you've read it. I
>> haven't. What's it about?
>> Oh, highly recommended by Oliver. Oh,
man. I'm gonna pull out the last name.
But 4,000 weeks. Uh, his idea is that
the the average one of us probably has
about 4,000 weeks. And you've probably
seen the Tim Urban like cartoon where he
draws out like a single box for every
week of his whole life, right? When you
think about a life as 4,000 weeks, it
actually feels a lot more precious and
every week feels much more
consequential. So reading that book
really helped me take a broader look
around. Decisions were often hard for me
because my values weren't clear. But
what I would say to the average person
if they're willing to hear the advice
would be something like, you know, first
visualize today's biggest goal for
yourself in the next whatever many
years. Like maybe you want to retire by
the time you're 36 or whatever the fire
people want, right? Um visualize that
goal. Then I would say now pretend
you've just reached it. What do you do
next? If you have a good answer for
that, then you're fine, you know? then
you'll be just fine. I did not have an
answer for that and being that person uh
not having that ready answer really left
me in a place where I was like uh is it
Michael Phelps or whoever like there's
so many athletes for whom once you reach
that career peak like they realize like
wait what's after football or what's
after swimming like and the answer is
nothing because they've built no other
skills in any other domain and once
they're not a famous football player
it's like well how many people really
want to see them and for what reasons
other than to ask them for money and so
I feel like many People have that big
goal. I'm going to get in the NFL. I'm
going to get in the NBA, right? But they
don't know what they're going to do the
day after. And so, if I could give one
piece of advice to people, it would be
like think about the day after and what
you're going to do. And I think the book
4,000 Weeks really helps a person think
about that.
>> And I guess last question, if you could
go all the way back to the beginning and
do it over again, is there anything that
you would change?
I think there were a few times in my
career where I think I biased too much
toward being maximally available for my
employer and not available at all for
friends or family. I think there were a
few incidents. Um, and I think if I
could change things again, I would have
played those periods of my life
differently. Funny enough, one of them
was not when I lost 10 pounds working
six weeks at Facebook because funny
enough, my kids were very young back
then, right? Like probably like three
and one or something. But what was great
was I told my wife back then, "Hey,
after we ship, it's probably going to be
nuts." And so what we did was we just
moved the whole family down to
California. [laughter]
And so like my wife took the kids to the
library every day. I could see them for
14 minutes before I went to sleep,
right? and like having family with me
and just treating it more like, hey
everybody, we're just going to go on a
big trip. That actually made it all
right. Whereas I think there were other
times in my career where, you know, my
wife was the primary one taking the kids
to and from school. I had very little
conversation with them. Um it felt like
I was doing important things quote
unquote for the family, right? But at
the same time, um I wasn't with the
family. And so there are times like that
where I do think there were a few
periods where I would have played that
differently.
Everything in life, we have limited
time. So everything in life, there's
tradeoffs.
If you did, let's just say you went back
to those times and you prioritized
family, would that have made a material
difference in your career success?
>> I think it might have. And I think the
trade-off
is in my case definitely worth it. Um, I
say I think it might have because it's
very hard to tell. Like I'll I'll throw
out examples where it's hard to tell.
You know how sometimes there's the type
of engineer who works like super long
hours, but you can tell that as they
work longer and longer, they're actually
creating more and more progressions and
they're like getting worse and worse,
right? For that sort of person, like a
break would actually improve their
performance. So there's no telling for
which like maybe sometimes taking a
break would have made me actually
perform even better, right? So, I don't
want to say that that's definitely not
true, but I also feel for the type of
person who constantly tells other
people, "Relax, work a 40-hour work
week. You'll do just as well and even
better than other people." I don't think
that's in general true. Like, I think
just at the face of it, it doesn't seem
like it could be true. If two people
were the same skill level, right, but
one just worked 10 hours more per week
over a period of time, I think anybody
would feel it was grossly unfair if that
person wasn't rewarded any differently.
Like it would feel like what? Like what
sort of crazy company do you work for
where like these two people get
compensated the identical amount over
multiple years, but one guy's working
40% more, right? It makes no sense. So,
I do suspect it would have impacted
career, but I think also that I would
have gladly taken that trade-off.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
your time, Phil. I really appreciate it.
>> Yeah, thanks for having me again.
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like. Also, if you have any
recommendations for people you want me
to bring on, please drop a comment.
guests like Barbara Liskov, Mike
Stonereaker, Mark Brooker. These were
all people that I brought on because
someone left a comment. On another note,
aside from the podcast, I'm working on
building the ergonomic keyboard that I
wish existed. Here's a glance at the
prototype. It's a split keyboard, so
there's two sides. Um, this is in the
case, but yeah, we launched on
Kickstarter and we hit our goal within
eight hours of launching. I really
appreciate it if you were one of the
people who grabbed one of the early
units. Um, we're now working on the long
journey of building the tooling now. And
so if you still want to pick one up,
I've left the late pledges open on
Kickstarter, so you can grab one there.
I'll put a link in the description.
Thank you again for watching the podcast
and I'll see you in the next